<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nevves from Turkie and Poland. Or A true and compendious declaration of the proceedings betweene the great Turke, and his Maiestie of Poland, from the beginning of the warres, vntill the latter end VVith a relation of their daily millitary actions; shewing plainly how the warre continued and ended, peace was concluded, the troubles appeased, the articles of agreement confirmed, and a full league of amity ratified. Translated out of a Latine copie, written by a gentleman of quality, who was an actor in all the businesse: and now with his consent published.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08154</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.36</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118695</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853902</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853902</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19303</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08154)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19303)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 942:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nevves from Turkie and Poland. Or A true and compendious declaration of the proceedings betweene the great Turke, and his Maiestie of Poland, from the beginning of the warres, vntill the latter end VVith a relation of their daily millitary actions; shewing plainly how the warre continued and ended, peace was concluded, the troubles appeased, the articles of agreement confirmed, and a full league of amity ratified. Translated out of a Latine copie, written by a gentleman of quality, who was an actor in all the businesse: and now with his consent published.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 49, 30-31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Edward Allde],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at the Hage [i.e. London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Latin original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Actual place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 24332 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Turkey --  History --  Wars with Persia, 1618-1622 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Poland --  History --  Sigismund III, 1587-1632 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19303:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19303:1"/>
            <p>NEWES From Turkie and Poland.</p>
            <p>OR A TRVE AND COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious declaration of the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings betweene the great Turke, and his Maieſtie of POLAND, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Warres, vntill the latter end.</p>
            <p>With a Relation of their daily Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary actions; ſhewing plainly how the Warre continued and ended, peace was concluded, the troubles appeaſed, the Articles of agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment confirmed, and a ful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> league <hi>of amity ratified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of a Latine Copie, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               </hi>ten by a Gentleman of quality, who was an <hi>Actor in all the buſineſſe: And now with his conſent publiſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at the Hage. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quote">
            <pb facs="tcp:19303:2"/>
            <q>
               <p>—Pax optima rerum</p>
               <p>Quas homini nouiſſe datum eſt, pax vna triumphis Innumeris potior, pax cuſtodire ſalutem Et ciues aequare potens.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Silius Italic. lib. 1. bel. punicum.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19303:2"/>
            <head>A TRVE RELATION OF THE DAILY CONFLICTS, and proceedings betweene the great Turkes Armie, and his Maieſtie of POLAND, <hi>to the end of the Warres.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here ſhall neede no preamble, nor inſinuation to this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, more then that you haue had already a publiſhed Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let of the newes of Poland, ſhewing plainely the occaſion of the Turkes formidable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration againſt that Country, with his deſcending in perſon into Walachia, and comming to many skirmiſhes and battailes, afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as many rumors of the ſeuerall euents and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes in the ſame; inſomuch that many reported Poland was ouer-runne, and <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> ſlaine: Yet there is but one truth which that booke in generall ſets out: yet ſo farre ſhort of ſatisfaction, that it comes not neere any particular indeede, whereby men went away, as if they had onely looked on the outward painting and brauery of a houſe, without once being admitted to ouer-looke, how neceſſary
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19303:3"/> and conuenient it was in the inward roomes. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will promiſe you amends, though in a plaine faſhion, and this relation ſhall ſupply the defects of the other. For I will preſently come to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and begin with the beginning of September: after the Polacks had entrenched themſelues, and the Turkes and Tartars came as neere them as might be.</p>
            <p>Know then, that the ſecond of September <hi>ſtilo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> the Turkes and Tartars encamped themſelues by vs within a mile, or halfe a mile, and the ſame day began hotly vpon vs, brauing our trenches, which we would not endure, but came to blowes, and made a skirmiſh, in which eight hundred Turks periſhed, as by many Captiues and Priſoners, which we tooke in the flight, was afterward confeſſed, beſides ſuch as were ſlaine neere hand in the charges, and farre off with the Bullets, both of our field Peeces and Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>katieres: on our ſide periſhed <hi>Tarouits</hi> and <hi>Bochdan,</hi> two Commaunders of Light-horſe, and the Lord <hi>Lauizza</hi> of the Cohort of the Camp-Maſter, was ſhot in the foot with a great Bullet, two Maſters of the beſt men of Armes ſlaine, and aboue 30. other of ſeuerall Companies hurt.</p>
            <p>The third of September, they proceeded in the ſame manner, and we with ſome light excurſions ſet vpon them, till at laſt they burſt out in three ſeuerall parts againſt our trenches, eſpecially where our Coſſacks were quartred, and ſo came to the very out-skirts of our Poliſh Army, who had command to keepe themſelues within their Tents and Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19303:3"/> and annoy the Turkes with their great Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, and ſo we proſpered for that time, driuing them into their Campe, wherein by Sunne-ſetting they quickly retired: the ſame euening our noble Prince paſſed ouer the Riuer, and came into our Campe with all manner of comfort and courage, but the Army he brought with him, with prouiſion of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Ordnance, and other Munition neceſſary for vs, could not come at vs, by reaſon the Bridge brake by the force of the water, which not three dayes before they had builded vp and erected.</p>
            <p>The fourth of September, by the Sunne riſing, the Emperour of Turkes, would needs in perſon be a beholder of the skirmiſh, and ſo in a manner ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proched the Campe of the Coſſacks, bringing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny field Peeces, and mounting ſuch, which they call <hi>Ianſcharki,</hi> and ſo a great battaile began, which la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted full fiue houres: For the Coſſacks much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damnified by the Artillary, made ſo braue a ſalley vpon the Turkes, that they draue them backe by maine force, and put a number of them to the ſword, inſomuch that they altered their determination, and brought their <hi>Ianskarks</hi> before the quarter, where the Camp-Maſter was lodged, but here it was too hot for them: and it did not ſucceed, as they expected, ſo they charged the Coſſacks once againe, riding by our trenches in a brauing manner, and comming vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them with an inſulting violence, which yet proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered not, as they expected: whereupon not an houre before Sunne ſetting, they charged them more violently, but God was our defence at this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19303:4"/> time: For the Coſſacks made ſo braue a ſalley, that they put the Turkes to flight euen to their Tents, with ſuch a ſlaughter, and ſuch a ſucceſſe, that they ſurpriſed their Artillery, tooke many Tents, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with them much furniture, and ſo returned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dark night with the booty, to their own Camp and lodging.</p>
            <p>The fift of December, we were quiet on both ſides: For the Turkes remoued their quarter a little more backward, yet with full reſolution to ſet vpon vs againe, as by many priſoners we tooke was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed: whereupon we fell to our accuſtomed pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to God, and about noone there fell a raine, and ſo there was nothing attempted that day, but that we prepared our ſelues for the expugnation.</p>
            <p>The ſixt of September, there fled vnto vs a Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack, one of the inhabitants by the riuer of Danu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius, who had beene ſeauen yeare in ſeruitude with the Turkes, and affirmed, that there were ſlaine 2000. Ianiſſaries in the laſt skirmiſhes, and expu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puation of our Camp; that the great Turke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe would lead the whole Army in perſon, except ſuch as he muſt needs leaue for the defence of his Camp, and the ſecurity of his cattell: that already there began to be a great dearth amongſt them. For foure pound of bread was worth 24. Aſpers of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and a quantity of Barly or other Corne, equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the halfe buſhell of the meaſure of Camenenſis, was valued at ſeauen Florins, and 15. Aſpers, and that many diſcontents appeared amongſt them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. The ſame day there came alſo vnto vs a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19303:4"/> Dutch man, who had falne into the hands of the Turkes, as a priſoner with a Captaine of the Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacks, and he aſſured vs that on Friday <hi>Aſis Baſſaw,</hi> a man of great reputation among the Turkes, was ſtruck in the forehead with a Bullet, and ſo ſlaine; and that ſo many Turkes were ouerthrowne in the laſt ſeuerall on-ſets vpon the Coſſacks, that they began to flye euery where from their quarter and Cabbines: he alſo related the cauſe, why the Turks were ſo quiet, which was by reaſon of a larges, or donation of money the Turke beſtowed vpon ſuch, who had behaued themſelues well in the laſt enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, preparing for new aſſaults: and this was the truth of the matter.</p>
            <p>The ſeauenth of September the Turkes came vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs againe in the after noone, and very outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in great companies aſſaulted our Bulwarkes, which were yet vnperfected, and lay ſomewhat naked to oppoſition, aſcending the ſame, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as it were poſſeſſion: but with equall loſſe, as it appeared for the time, vntill the noble Lord <hi>Steward</hi> of the Kingdome, who came there by chance with his troope of Horſe, ſet vpon them moſt valiantly, and by the aſſiſtance of the Lord <hi>Caſtellano Plocen,</hi> and <hi>P. Radomina,</hi> put them off the walls to a fore-flight, as farre as the wood ſcited euen before the Turkes Campe, whether they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them in the ſlaughter: as for ſuch Turkes as at firſt dared to approach our Trenches, and ſcale our Mounts, they all periſhed vpon them, we not looſing aboue twelue men of Armes in that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19303:5"/> ſeruice, with ſome few other hurt, except <hi>Caſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Plocen,</hi> who with many wounds returned, and died the next day: But the aſſault againſt the Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacks endured from noone to night; ours onely laſted from the after-noone to Sunne ſetting, yet both continued with ſo fearefull effects, that the multitude of the ſlaughtred was apparant, and the Enemies carkaſſes lay in heapes in the fields: Yea, it was remarkeable, how all that night the Turks made a ſearch with lighted fire-brands, and other Lamps, for ſome perſon of account amongſt the dead bodies, which as ſome of their owne fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues affirmed, was one of the <hi>Viceer Baſſas,</hi> who was miſſing, and could not be found.</p>
            <p>The eighth of September, there eſcaped out of the Turkes hands a Coſſack, who had long laine in fetters, he came to vs by night, and tolde vs plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the Turkes had loaden many Cammels with the encumbrances of the Army, and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the cariage Horſes, as if they meant to make ſome retreat: notwithſtanding, the ſame day very inconſiderately they came vpon the Coſſacks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, who by the helpe of the Germanes now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them; both defended themſelues, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended their Enemies: for here were braue Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunders, partly vnder the Regiment and conduct of Captaine <hi>Drhuſoff,</hi> partly vnder Captaine <hi>Ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund,</hi> and of the other ſide in the right wing, there were the Cohorts of his Excellency, the Lord <hi>Palatine.</hi> The ſame day <hi>Schandactus</hi> cut off by the ſword, according to the manner and cuſtome
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19303:5"/> of a Military Court, who adiudged him to die, a principall Captaine of the Coſſacks, called <hi>Bron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danka,</hi> who the yeare before had abuſed his prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue, and moſt peruerſly by factious deuiſes, and apparant thefts, had tranſcended the gouernment of a Commaunder in chiefe, and falne to thefts and robberies more then neceſſity, or the preſent wants enforced.</p>
            <p>The ſame day a certaine Squire eſcaped out of the hands of the Turkes, who was vnfortunately taken priſoner at a battaile in Cicora, and came vnto vs, affirming confidently, that ſince the Turkes comming into the field, there are dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at leaſt twelue thouſand of their number, ſome ſlaine out-right, ſome dying of their woundes, ſome ſurpriſed in the Campe, and ſome flying away.</p>
            <p>The ninth of September, the great Turke after noone drew out all his Army in battaile array: which Lord <hi>Magnus</hi> our Generall perceiuing, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted no time, but prepared for the fight: ſo that both Armies euen to Sunne ſetting, ſtood loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vpon one another, without any mans giuing the ſigne of the battaile, not daring to approach too neere the fortifications, and Bulwarkes of our Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; but ſtood as remote as they could, and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt from danger. In the meane while, the Iani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries fell foule vpon the quarter of the Coſſacks againe, and continued little leſſe then foure houres in a dangerous skirmiſh: For the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes playing their part on the other ſide, as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19303:6"/> aſſiſting the Coſſacks in their Warre-like excur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, quickly, when they preſſed them with fury and impetuoſity, compelled them backe to their Campe, and wee returned to our Trenches: But the ſame night another priſoner eſcaped, and came vnto vs, affirming that of the Spahies, who were the forwardeſt in this expugnation, as ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by the Captaine of the Ianizaries, loſt two hundred of their Company, and of the Iani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaries were ſlaine, with ſuch as periſhed in the flight 1500.</p>
            <p>The tenth of September, the Turkes were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what quiet, as peraduenture wearied with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer dayes miſchiefe, and we farre apparant the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious chances of Warre, and the wonderfull eſſects of a Battaile.</p>
            <p>The eleuenth of September, the Turkes made a new apparance out of their Tents, with a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Army: and wee were not behinde to Marſhall our Companies to as braue a ſhow: but nothing was done that day, and ſo wee returned on all ſides to lodging: yet while wee remained in this expectation, the Turkes had tranſported their Ordnance to the other ſide of the Riuer, from whence hee played continually into the quarters of the Coſſacks all that day: but when hee ſaw, they did them no more harme, hee quickly drew them backe againe; and placed them more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely: The ſame day, ſome thouſands of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars ſhewed themſelues on that ſide of the Riuer alſo; who with their accuſtomed clamours and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19303:6"/> out-cry, attempted the breaking of our Bridge: but onely two hundred foot, whereof one was kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and two hurt with Bullet, preſſed vpon them with ſuch volleyes of ſhot, that they were quickly put to flight. God graunt wee may be thankfull for theſe things. For without controuerſie, Gods onely hand hath protected vs, that both on the one ſide the Turke is more remiſſe then his former threatnings, and this preſent appearance promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and we on the other ſide we haue had greater courages, and better ſucceſſe then wee could any manner of way expect.</p>
            <p>The twelfth of September, a little after mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, wee determined to ſet vpon the Campe of our Aduerſaries, leauing our noble Prince ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently guarded within the Trenches, as not well at eaſe, and ſo the Army deuided it ſelfe into parts, hauing inſtructions to come vpon them vnawares: the one to compaſſe the Woods, and ſet vpon them in the reare, and at their backes: the other to out-face them in the front and ſides, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing might be done euery way. But it pleaſed God to ſend ſo great a ſhower of raine, that wee were diuerted from our purpoſes at this time: but I make no queſtion of a better opportunity, and that our Aduerſaries little knew of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, and ſo wee may once againe ſee the ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem on foot, till when wee retired to our Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſecurely.</p>
            <p>The 15. of September, the Turkes and Tartars,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19303:7"/> with a great reſolution and impetuous aſſault, preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed both vpon vs, and the Coſſacks in three ſeuerall partes, neither fearing our Artillery, nor making accompt of our Trenches: the great Turke himſelfe being a ſpectator on an eminent Hill, whoſe youth apprehended the miſchiefe but as a ſport. For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manner of remorce for the periſhing of ſo many thouſands, they came forward like furious beaſts without Diſcipline or order, and ſo periſhed like Beaſts, when the Artillery played vpon them, and wee ruſhed out as violently well armed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in the ſmoake againſt them, this Battaile laſted from Noone to Night, and the God of Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes for his mercy ſake, did fruſtrate and annihilate both the purpoſe and the rage and fury of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, nor ended it ſo, but for his Glories ſake wee preuailed with a great ſlaughter, and little loſſe on our ſide: So that it ſhould ſeeme all their threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and fury was in vaine, concerning the attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of our Trenches, and the Angels of the Lord ſpred his winges ouer our Tents: On the other ſide our Souldiers were ſo couragious, and animated, as infuſed with new Spirits from the ſame God, that they not onely ruſhed out of the portes and paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of their Quarters vpon their Enemies, but hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried ouer the Trenches and Ditches to forward the enterpriſe, and ſo came to handiblowes, and with extraordinary valour and ſlaughter ſent them home againe.</p>
            <p>In this Skirmiſh we did not altogether goe ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>free, but ſaw the periſhing of thouſands of Turkes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19303:7"/> and Tartars, whoſe Carkaſſes beſpred the ground as it were: and among whome there periſhed the great Baſhaw ſurnamed <hi>Koraken,</hi> who newly came to the Emperour and was moſt deare vnto him, and well accepted of him: the ſame Fate and triall had <hi>Naſſan Baſſaw</hi> with many Chawſes and Spahies, and a number vnnumbred of common Souldiers.</p>
            <p>After this ſlaughter the Turkes attempted no more the expugnation of our Campe, except that once they did inuade the quarter of the Coſſacks, but with the like ſucceſſe, yet many times they brought out their Armies to open view, and as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times God of his mercy made way to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailings, and wee returned Victors: The ſame day the Bridge was finiſhed, which they had a while a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe begun ouer the Riuer, that diuided their Campes: but to what purpoſe is not knowne, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to accommodate their paſſages the better: now alſo returned the Lord <hi>Siclentius,</hi> who had bin ſent into the Palatinate of Moldauia with anſwer to a Letter, which they ſent before, but what other newes he brought, is not apparant: It was alſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, that a rumour was ſpred into the Turkes campe, that the Sacred Maieſty of <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> the King our Maſter, was come into the Field with a Royall ſupply, and generall expedition, which a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle affrighted the Tartars, who were now to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt fortifications and Armed men, contrary to their barbarous cuſtome of deuouring one another naked.</p>
            <p>The 17. of September, our great Lord Generall
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19303:8"/> held a martiall Counſell with the Lord Senators, Dukes, Gouernors, and Captaines, to which were alſo called the Lord <hi>Sahaidace,</hi> Generall of the Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſackes with all his Colonels, and Officers, who with one voyce, and vnanimity of Spirit concluded and agreed, rather to die manfully in the field, then to goe backe one foot of ground, to giue the Enemy cauſe of preſumption: and this was done with ſuch generall alacrity, that although both the Armies, I meane, the Polonians and Coſſacks, were in great diſtreſſe and wants; yet they concluded, that by Gods grace, they would not be terrefied with any Enemy.</p>
            <p>The 18. of September, certaine troopes of horſe, and Companies of foot, made a ſalley out of the Coſſacks quarter in the night vpon the Turkes Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, which was done ſo ſecretly and ſuddenly, that they ouer-turned many Tents, ranſacked diuers Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins, and killed ſome hundreds of men with Iaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, Pollaxes, and Launces, without the report of a Peece, or carrying any Artillery with them: yea, herein they were ſo fortunate, that they returned with great ſpoile, without the loſſe of a man. The next night they performed as much, and with the like ſtratagem ſet vpon the Bridge they had newly builded &amp; erected, and ſlew <hi>Corkan Baſſaw,</hi> to whoſe cuſtody and charge it was committed. They alſo killed many Turks, tooke nine priſoners, and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with great ſpoiles and a rich prey, wherein were diuers garments furred with coſtly Furres, which I thinke, the Turkes vſe among the Tartars, who vpon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19303:8"/> many excurſions, made into Ruſſia by thouſand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in theſe dayes, returned with a wonderfull ſpoile, ſelling them at a price to the Turks: and this was done euen as they came along to take vp their lodgings in theſe Prouinces.</p>
            <p>At this time his Excellency, the Lord Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, was ſubiect to a great ſickneſſe, which ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired his health, that he feared his life: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon he ſummoned all Officers, and referred his gouernment to the Lord <hi>Campe,</hi> Maſter Generall, with all Millitary priuiledges, and imperiall fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, inueſting vpon him as farre as he could his dignity and authority; yet were the whole Army deſirous to ſee the heroick Prince himſelfe moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on horſe-backe, as their Commaunder Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, though as yet very young, ſo that by this ioy and good mindes of the Army, he was much comforted, and incited to thanke them all, and be the more gracious vnto them, when time ſhould ſerue.</p>
            <p>The 24. of September, hauing layne quiet a great while, an accident at home diſquieted vs all: For our great Lord Generall, labouring long in his ſickneſſe, and being wearied and ſpent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with intollerable convulſions, and diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature of the ayre, yeelded to the commaund of a higher Generall, and ſo died in the Camp.</p>
            <p>The 25. of September, the Emperour of Turks made a great preperation to ſet vpon vs on all ſides, drawing out from their ſeuerall Quarters,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19303:9"/> both Horſe, Foot, and Artillery, to oppreſſe and expugne vs with an vnreſiſtable power; and ſo they approached our Trenches with accuſtomed clamours and out-cries: but the ſame God, that kept vs from the beginning, continued ſtill our Protector, and all their attempts were annihila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, turning rather to the deſtruction of many of their owne Souldiers, then to our detriment.</p>
            <p>The 26. of September, <hi>Baptiſta</hi> was diſpatched, who was ſent vnto vs from the Palatine of Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauia, with Letters and other intelligence: hee came but the Tueſday before with the Lord of Zielenskij, who aſſured vs, that the Turkes had a great deſire to treat of a peace; and therefore <hi>Baptiſta</hi> had in charge to deale with the Viceer, for ſafe conduct of ſuch Commiſſioners, as might be ſent to tractate about the peace and quietneſſe of both Armies.</p>
            <p>Within three dayes our Souldiers ſet vpon ſome part of the Tartars Quarter, as being much diſpleaſed, that the paſſages were ſtopped vp by them: whereby the Souldiers that went a forra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, and to gather fodder and litter for their Horſes, were much diappointed: ſo that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge they put many to the ſword, and ſet their Quarter on fire.</p>
            <p>The 27. of September, the Turkes hauing ſtrongly mounted diuers great Peeces, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced their Gabbions about them, as is the cuſtome, played fearefully into the Coſſacks Quarter, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19303:9"/> ſpent all the fore-noone in the ſending hundreds of Bullets among them: but when they percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that it ſmally auailed, they deſiſted, and made a new attempt in their owne perſons neerer vnto them: which when the Coſſacks perceiued, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loath to be out-braued at their owne walls, as I may ſay, or encouraged by the thriuings of many out-roades and excurſions they had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly made: or emboldned by their owne ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, or preſuming on the weakneſſe, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of their Aduerſaries, I might adde their barbarous haſtineſſe, and beſtiall howlings and out-cries; they ſallyed out brauely, with the moſt part of their Army, and compulſed them backe, driuing them into their Quarters with a great ſlaughter, and a great ſpeedineſſe: and the ſame day, to the comfort of vs all, our noble Prince, whoſe long vntimely ſickneſſe, as it were, ſadded our hearts, recouered ſome ſtrength, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding round about the Army, being entertained with great ſhowts and acclamations of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and ſhewing in himſelfe apparant ſignes of recouery, as hauing layne vnder the ſhakings of a fearefull Ague, almoſt euer ſince wee encamped our ſelues, to whom the King did daily ſend Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, and Meſſengers, and would willingly haue come himſelfe in perſon; but that all his Peeres and Counſailours would not hazard all at once, conſidering what a formidable Enemy had threatned him, and fearefull preperation in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19303:10"/> circumcepted him: therefore they proiected to keepe him as a ſecond, and that ſecurely, that if the Turkes ſhould preuaile (which God forbid) againſt theſe Forces well ordered and marſhalled within theſe Trenches: there might yet a new Muſter be made, and Army trayned, whom the preſence of a King, and worthineſſe of ſo great a Commander might bring together, and ſet vpon the Triumpher with freſh ſupplies.</p>
            <p>But oh thou God! What an alteration was here? He that threatned theſe Polonians with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting oſtentation, by Ambaſſies, Letters, and an innumerable company of Mahumetans and Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians: he that had denounced defiance againſt all Chriſtendome: he that had ſpoken preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous words againſt any force, ſhould come by way of oppoſition: he that aduentured his perſon as farre as his greatneſſe might deſcend, to be a Spectator of this wofull Tragedy, wherein the miniſters of Warre and deſtruction muſt play their parts, and he which had brought one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred caſt Peeces into the field, to batter all forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications into rubbiſh: had now an anſwere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned of ſtrange contradiction, had now his threats retorted with as auaileable menaces, had now his rages ſent backe againe with vnexpected fury, had now his preſumption rebated with as noble a defiance, had now his way blocked vp and intercepted, that hee could not ſo quickly come ouer Palliſados, and Trenches, had now
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19303:10"/> Cannon to Cannon, battery to battery, and though not ſo many, as himſelfe brought, yet ſo well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and ſo efficatious in the deſignes, that hee was not ſo forward in his glory as he determined, nor ſo furious in any execution, as hee promiſed: Nay, if it had beene as well knowne to vs as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he repented that euer he came into the fields of Walachia, and as you ſhall heare hereafter, both retracted his firſt arrogancy, and whiſpered a peace, though hee durſt not ſpeake it aloud, for feare of the Ianizaries.</p>
            <p>But oh you ſonnes of men! what ſay you to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and the credulity of vncertaine reports? what ſay you to paſſion, and the diſordered burſtings out of your owne wiſhes? What ſay you to affrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, that becauſe you heare of the greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, will therefore preſently ſhew the greater par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality? How often within this twelue moneth hath Bogdonia beene ranſacked, Podolia diſtreſſed, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia ouer-runne, <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> ſlaine, and the Army diſcomfited, and yet (thanks be to God) the trenches were neuer caſt downe, the Souldiers diſarmed, the troopes ſlaughtred, the King in danger: (For he was ſcarce in the field at all) or any fearefull loſſe endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, more then they that muſt be loſt in ſo many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts, and ſuch impetuous aſſaults: and thus much by way of tranſition. Now to our buſineſſe againe.</p>
            <p>The ſame night, that the Prince had ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the day before the Coſſacks being ſet vpon, as you haue heard, ſuddenly aſſaulted the Quarter of their enemies, eſpecially the <hi>Tartars,</hi> who lay without
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19303:11"/> any manner of diſcipline, or ſtrong fortifications: yea, this they did twice in one night, and that with ſuch ſucceſſe, that beſides the ſlaughter, and hauock they made, they returned with great ſpoiles, and booty, yea greater then the Enemy could ſpare, or were willing to looſe; this they did often, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſometimes their actions were obumbrated with ſome diſcomfiture: yet did they neuer make any ſalley, without the greater ſlaughter of their Enemies. Now is <hi>Baptiſta</hi> come backe againe from the Enemies Campe, bringing Letters from <hi>Veſin Basſha,</hi> of ſafe conduct and admiſſion, as he himſelfe had had experience by himſelfe for ſuch Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, as the King of Poland would put in truſt for the diſpatch of ſo high affaires: yea, he ſaid plainly, as farre as he could coniecture, that neuer was any thing ſo pleaſing to the Turke and his Souldiers, as the name of peace, conſidering the times, and the manner of the Warre; eſpecially that his reputation was ſaued by the firſt ſeeking it by the Polonians: wherein he vſed this pollicy, to make the Ianizaries beleeue, he was of himſelfe vnwilling to darken the glory of the Othoman family, by demanding peace himſelfe at any inferiour Nation in the world.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all this motiue of quietneſſe, which <hi>Baptiſtas</hi> Letters demonſtrated, might come to equall concluſion by orderly Commiſſioners. The Grand Signieur proiected with all the force, brauery, and pollicy he could, to ſet vpon the Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacks againe, who were his Aunceſtors Enemies, and more obnoxious vnto him, then any neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19303:11"/> whatſoeuer: and becauſe he would make, as it were ſure worke of the matter, hee acquainted <hi>Tartar Chrim,</hi> who they ſay accompanied him to the Warre with the ſame, and he either of neceſſity obeying, or out of cuſtome conſenting, or for his owne reuenges willing, quickly accord, and by breake of day brought all his Tartars to the place appointed for the expugnation: whereupon they ordered the matter ſo, that in the manner of a ring they compaſſed our Trenches round about: firſt playing ouer their heads into our Camps, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great Ordnance, which were mounted in three ſeuerall places; then tranſported they ouer the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thirty more, which continually beat both vpon ours, the Liſſauonians, and the Coſſacks Tents, and that for the ſpace of diuers houres, ſending likewiſe fiery Speares, burning Darts, and ſulphury Balls a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, inſomuch that our Prince lying yet ſicke in his Tent, had the Captaine of his Guard ſlaine with a Bullet. Among the Liſſauonians three of the beſt men of Armes were killed outright: and among the Coſſacks one or two hurt.</p>
            <p>After this, with ſtrange aſſaults and fearefull vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, they preſſed vpon the two ſpeciall paſſages of our Camp: whereat the one ſtood firme, the Lord <hi>Campe</hi> Maſter Generall, with a great and ſtrong Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion: at the other, the Lord <hi>Palatine Culmenſis:</hi> in the Market-place, the Lord <hi>Doenhoff,</hi> with many Germanes: in a word, wee were all in Armes, and the Cannons played on both ſides as farre as they could, for hurting thoſe in their owne Quarters: at
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19303:12"/> laſt on a ſuddaine with accuſtomed cry the Tartars gaue on, and were ready to ſcale the Trenches &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in at the Ports. Then followed the Ianizaries, as their ſeconds, and laſtly, the Spahies and Chawſes on Horſebacke, who by their brauery made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſure of the entrance, for the truth is we gaue ground, and loſt many men: For they preſſed ſo thicke vpon vs, that our ſhot did no good, and wee came to handy blowes within our owne Trenches, till certaine Coſſacks on that quarter, and Maſters of Pole on ours, finding the Tartars diſordered and diſarmed, ruſhed vpon them with fury, that they were driuen as faſt back againe, as they came in, and in a manner bare the Ianizaries downe, and puſled them much with their violence: yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding freſh men were ſtil ſent forwar, d who with a ſtrange pertinacity, &amp; vnchangeable valour, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued till Sun-ſet in the expugnation: ſo that in my conſcience, if they had beene Armed, and diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned after the manner of the warlike Nations of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, they had made a ſhrewde aduenture, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened a gap of entrance into our Countrey, and then (God knowes) whether this inundation would haue runne. For you ſee, when raging Seas beate vpon the bankes of low grounds, if they preuaile in bearing them before them, whole Countries are ſwallowed vp in the Vaſt paunch of the Ocean: But the ſame God, that puts a hooke in the noſtrils of <hi>Leuiatham,</hi> and bindeth <hi>Bebemoth</hi> with a chayne, ſet a limitation for theſe raging Mahumetans, and furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and barbarous Tartarians, ouer which they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19303:12"/> ſhould not paſſe at this time.</p>
            <p>For although they come with reſolution to force our Trenches, and ſo to lay the way open to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looke thoſe fieldes of Bogdonia with a curious eye, and put it thus to a braue tryall, diuiding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in many Troopes to take aduantage of our weaknes, and ſhrinking in this tempeſtuous ſtorme, yet (God bethanked) with our accuſtomed conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy we kept our ground, and though with ſome loſſe conſtrayned them to let goe the hold they had, and in the end with a great ſhame and a greater ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they hid their heades within their owne hedges: yea, they that euer ſcorned to quarter themſelues within Ditches, and for their infinite multitudes (with deſire of expedition) would neuer conſent to caſt vp a Trench, were now compelled to thinke vpon ſecurity, and haue a retiring place to goe too as a refuge.</p>
            <p>The 29. of September, there was great ſilence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and a meſſenger came for intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a while, that they might bury their Dead, which was a worke indeed reciprocall betweene vs, and ſo the time was ſpent in cleering the way of the dead Carkaſſes betweene our Campes, which being a full myle broad, lay all be-ſpred with dead bodyes, wherein we alſo had a ſhare, and the ſame cauſe of ſetting ourſelues on worke: For many Tartars had conuaied themſelues ouer the Riuer, and taking ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage of our encounter, thought we had left the backſide of our Campe, as it were naked and vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, but when they came, they found the Carts,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19303:13"/> Waggons, and Carriages, ſo ſtrongly to Barricado it, that they thought it in vaine to hazard them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and ſo returned diſappointed: yet becauſe they would be doing, they threw wild-fire amongſt the carriages, and put the Cattle in a great feare, whoſe roarings and bellowings amazed vs much, and in a manner begged reliefe at our hands, ſo that we thought it meete to ſend out certaine Troopes of Horſe, who fell vpon them ſo opportunely, that they let in 200. Polaxes amongſt them, yea the very Pyoners came with their Pixes and hutches, and played their parts like men and Souldiers: So that in the end wee compelled them to ſwim ouer the Riuer backe againe.</p>
            <p>The next day being the 30. of September, certain fugitiues came vnto vs, and many Captiues of our owne Countrey-men, who aſſured vs that the Turkes loſt in that Conflict 3000. men, beſides thoſe which the Tartars left behinde on the other ſide of the Riuer: wee loſt outright beſides the wounded 300. amongſt whom was one Captaine of account, and two of the Princes Guard, who were well eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by him: But ſuch was the feare of this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, and appearance of danger, that many indeed fled into <hi>Poland</hi> with heauy newes of an ouerthrow, ſo that when rumour was once a running, it immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated a ball of Snow, which by often rowling grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth greater and greater, and in the end conſumeth like a Ball of ſnow, when the ſunne of Truth diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uech it into vapours, and conſumeth it to nothing with the heate of his reflixure.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:19303:13"/>
            <p>The ſame day was a Councell of Warre, and when we ſaw, that their reſolution was to ouer-run vs, and that if by any meanes we ſhould fayle in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, there would heere be made an entrance into our Country indeed, when we alſo vnderſtood they were as willing to the peace as our ſelues, ſo it might bee of our firſt ſeeking, wee concluded to make the aduenture, and temper the potion, which might cure the burning feauer of our diſquiet: and ſo the Lord <hi>Caſtellanus Belrenn,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadus Lublinnen,</hi> were appointed Commiſſioners to tractate with the Turkes about Articles of Peace, and ceſſation of Hoſtility: theſe had for their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants 20. of the beſt Gentlemen of our Campe, and the beſt furniſhed, beſides ſeruants with proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of neceſſaries, if they ſhould fayle in their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſie, and finde, a contrary doggednes in their enemies.</p>
            <p>By that time the Trumpets had giuen warning of their acceſſe, and that they approched very neere the Turkes Campe 200. Spahies and Chawſes on Horſebacke with Veluet Gownes, rich ſiluer Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and braue Turbanes, came to entertaine them, and bring them by way of conduction through the firſt Guard of Ianizaries, and ſo through many troopes of Horſe, and field Pieces mounted on de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate Carriages, till they came to the Tent of the Viceer, who welcommed him in his Maſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe: but according to former cuſtome hee muſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a while, ere hee could haue Anſwer from the <hi>Grand Signeur</hi> himſelfe, and peraduenture not ſpeake
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19303:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> with him at all: For you muſt know, that howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they were glad of compoſition, yet the Turke would not diſcouer any inclination to Peace, but if hee did condiſcend, it was meerly out of Heroyick compaſſion, not any neceſſity of his part: For du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of the treaty, the Hoſtility continued, and diuers excurſions had the effect of furious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters and bloody skirmiſhes.</p>
            <p>The firſt of October, the Lord <hi>Koskakorffskij</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned by night with all his Company and prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſafe to our Campe, hauing eſcaped many dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and conflicts with the Tartars, who being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with this purpoſe and Iourney, lay in waite to intercept his returne: For thus it was, prouiſion fayling in our Campe, and many neceſſaries wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting becauſe the Enemy had blocked vp diuers paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages and Riuers, whereby the inhabitants could not bring in prouiſion, as they were accuſtomed, it was concluded to ſend the Lord <hi>Koskakorffskij</hi> with Captaine <hi>Viſnen</hi> to the Towne Camenecen, with a ſufficient conuoy for prouiſion and victuall; who ſome 8. dayes before tooke his Iourney, which was not yet ſo couertly done, but both Turkes &amp; Tartars were acquainted with the ſame, apprehending that we muſt needs be in ſome diſtreſſe, &amp; that our wants were to bee ſupplyed from his endeauours in procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring new prouiſion, and therfore aduanced a ſtrong Battalion with many ſhot on foote, and diuers field Pieces to intercept his returne, and ſo lay betweene the Towne and our Campe, being not 15. nayle a ſunder: they tooke vp much ground, and were
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19303:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> diſperſed in many places, yea many times reſolued to ſet vpon the Towne it ſelfe, and if they could to take the ſpoyle of the ſame but it was too ſtrong for them, and ſo they contented themſelues in the expectation of this booty, and the returne of the Polonians to the Campe.</p>
            <p>When the Towne ſawe the Fieldes thus ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpred with Tartars, and that they were ſo well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to intercept the Carriages, they fortefied themſelues the ſtronger, and yet ment not to keepe themſelues within their Walles, conſidering the neceſſity of releeuing their Campe: but againe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding that they lay vpon euery paſſage, and muſt hazard the whole Conuoy with the prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the interception: the Lord <hi>Koskakorffskij,</hi> with the other Captaines, thought it beſt to put a tricke vpon their Enemies, and deceiue them if they could by a petty Stratagem, which they thus effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: When all thinges were ready for their returne within Eight dayes after their departure from the Campe, they ſet forward backe againe, with many Waggons of Wine and Corne, and ſo iſſued out with certaine Troopes well appointed, whom they flancked with light Waggons full of Strawe, and Hay, yet not ſo full but they went in a manner as faſt as the Horſe, which when the Tartars percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, they brought vp their Pieces and came for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with their ſhot, to diſ-rancke theſe Cartes, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſuppoſing the maine booty was in the midſt of the troopes: but the Cartes went ſo faſt, and the Horſe vpon the trot, that they were quickly from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19303:15"/> the ſhot of their Ordinance, and made the Tartars weary to follow them: yet as they were inſtructed they made diuers ſtands, as if the Waggons ment to take ſome reſt, and then as the Tartars approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched they would trot away againe, and thus they continued till night: by which time the Tartars were quickly drawne from the Towne, and thought it worke enough to ſecure the field Peeces from ſurprizing: When night came, then iſſued out the Lord <hi>Koskakorffskij</hi> with the mayne Conuoy indeed, which conſiſted of Corne, Oyle, Wine, Honey, and Cattle, and went a cleane contrary way vnknowne to the Enemy, though ſomewhat about to a Towne called <hi>Sarno Kouonicie,</hi> where he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modated to the Riuer of <hi>Iſter,</hi> and from whence he came to the Campe, as you haue heard in ſafety and good order: yet not without ſome oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though farre from loſſe and diſcomfiture: For by that time the Tartars knew how they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, which they did by light Horſemen ſent of purpoſe by the Polonians, to diuert them from fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing thoſe troopes that iſſued out of <hi>Cameneces</hi> by day too farre, they ſent word to the Turkes of the deceipt, and they exaſperated with very rage, ranne downe in whole Companies to beſet the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer on both ſides, and brought their Ordinance to play vpon the Boates, who kept the ſtreame, but the moſt were paſſed by ere they came; and the reſt kept the Channell, which was heere ſo broad, that the Ordinance played on the Banckes and could not doe them much harme: Yet did the Turkes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19303:15"/> follow them as farre as our Trenches, but we hauing certaine Towers well fortefied on both ſides the Riuer, played out of them ſo violently, that wee cut off ſome of them in their ſpeedines, and thoſe who were within reach of the ſhot of our Trenches, were faine to recoyle, and ſo the Turkes and Tartars re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned with great ſorrow on all ſides, to be thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed, and we entertained our friends with ioy on euery ſide to be thus releeued.</p>
            <p>The ſame day before Sun-ſetting, Ambaſſadors came to our Noble Prince from the Coſſackes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting the ſhore of the Blacke ſea by the mouth of Volga, and thoſe Riuers that powre themſelues as it were into the lap of <hi>Moeotis Palus,</hi> and thoſe borders of Ruſſia: The ſomme of their Ambaſcy was, that they had raiſed an Army of 20000. in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Chriſtians, againſt either Turke and Tartar, or any other Enemy, which ſhall blaſpheme their Religion; they were armed and payed and within a dayes march of the Campe: whether they were entertained by the Prince or no? Let all Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces iudge, who know the benefit of Auxiliary forces and friendly ſupplyes, comming opportunely, and in caſe of neceſſity, whether the newes was wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come? let a wounded and diſtreſſed perſon iudge who is puld out of a ditch from ſtaruing &amp; brought to good fires and better lodging: whether we made vſe of their company and coadiutement, let him iudge, that being ouermatched with raging aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, is on a ſodain ſupplyed with worthy ſeconds, who venture their liues in his defence: In a worde worde whether the Turkes vnderſtanding of their
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19303:16"/> approach: were not a little troubled, conſidering they had beene ſo often affronted already: let them judge that vnderſtand the nature of Conflicts, and the condition of ſupplies, though it bee but in Ambuſcadoes, which haue many times turned backe, fayling and diſcomfitted Troopes, and in a new tryall recouered the victory.</p>
            <p>word whether the Turks vnderſtanding of their</p>
            <p>The ſecond of October, wee tooke ſome Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and many came vnto vs of their owne accord; yea, diuers Captiues Chriſtians found away to eſcape, and deliuer themſelues from the Turkiſh ſlauery and bondage, and bee vnited againe to the Loue and Obedience of their mother Countrey, who all confidently affirmed, that the Turkes were weary of the Warre, and the Tartars cryed out of the walled Townes, fortefied Trenches, mounted Ordinance, arming Corſlets, long Pikes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Warlike preparation, contrary to their bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and Sauage nakedneſſe, and yet did they not deſiſt from their ſpoyles, and vnciuill forra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the Countrey, eſpecially if they could vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any aduantage, either ſet vpon vs, or ſurpriſe vs: but yet wee had no ſuch aduertiſement from our Commiſſioners, nor durſt disbandy our ſelues vpon any hopes, whatſoeuer: Onely this I will bee bolde to affirme, that if the Turkes did now deſire a Peace with vs, hee will not bee ſo forward to proclaime Warre againſt vs hereafter, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frindge the Conditions, when they bee once ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:19303:16"/>
            <p>From the third of October, to the ninth, the time was ſpent in diſputing about the peace: For the Hoſpodar of Walachia, with many Princes of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uia and Bulgaria, intruded themſelues, and deſired the Viceers and Baſhawes of the Turke to be inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the conditions. Heere ſome will haue the King of Poland to repaire into the Campe: ſome againe will haue him to come in with the Army of Coſſacks, that came from Volga and the black Sea: ſome will haue his Standard royall to be aduanced in the Army, before he came in perſon: ſome will haue him ſecretly to come in, without any brauery or oſtentation: howſoeuer it be; this is ſure, that he was neither mentioned, nor publickly ſeene, vntill the Treaty of Peace, and his marching to Leopolis, wherein likewiſe I finde ſome diſcrepancy about the time, which may be the miſtaking of <hi>ſtilo nouo,</hi> and <hi>ſtilo antiquo,</hi> or elſe the error conſiſted in the ſetting downe a generall riſing, when yet moſt part of the Army remained in the Trenches, after the King was departed, as you ſhall heare hereafter: howſoeuer; I finde no variation for the ſubſtance of matter, nor in truth any great matter after the peace to variate about, and ſo to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The ninth of October, the peace was concluded after the old conditions, and ratifications with the accuſtomed manner of proceedings, nor was there any manner of foederation left out, which might ſerue to glorifie the Common-wealthes on either ſide: From whence I onely obſerue, that by this meanes, this inſulting Enemy, who a little before,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19303:17"/> or if you will the Spring of the yeare, threatned fire and ſword, and was ſo farre from any conditions of amity, that he proclaimed the deuaſtation of our Countrey, and would haue no deniall, but vtter ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, tribute, and ſlauiſh obedience, by the force of Armes, ſaw now the ſtaffe of his mightineſſe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a pieces; and that in a manner by compulſion, he muſt make a peace with an inferiour Prince: and when? when we ſtood in need of prouiſion, wanted powder, and ſhot, ſaw a returdance in ſuch troopes and payments of money, as were promiſed by many Chriſtian Princes, had our Common-wealth tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moyled with the Warres of Liuonia, and our ſelues formerly wearied with many convulſions, now ſet vpon afreſh with the onely Enemies of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the great Turke, and barbarous Tartar: but this God can doe, and this God for vs, and the ſame God will (I hope) continue his mercy toward vs.</p>
            <p>The 11. of October, the Emperour of Turks ſent vnto his Maieſty a Meſſenger with theſe inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that we ſhould firſt raiſe our Camp, and depart out of Walachia, a Prouince ſubiect and tributary to him, which by no meane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we would agree vnto, proiecting altogether the dignity of the Kingdome, and the commodiouſneſſe of the Army, both which might haue beene impaired, nay all quite ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, if while we were puſled thus in riſing; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Turks breaking their couenants, might fall vpon vs; or ouer-taking vs in the Plaines, might preſſe vpon vs with the greater number, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouided. Whereupon the Turke leauing the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19303:17"/> ſtanding Bridge, which he made ouer the Riuer, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued his Camp ſome halfe mile backwarder, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs leaue to make vſe of the Bridge, either for carriages too and fro, or our orderly marches: but yet we ſtirred not for all this: no, though the Turke ſtayed two dayes in that place; inſomuch, that wee had recourſe one to another, and tooke a liberty to flatter one another with formall welcomes, feaſting, and kinde embraces, as is the cuſtome of reconciled friends, or if you will protected Enemies.</p>
            <p>The 12. of October, the Grand Signieur marched fiue mile further, to the Riuer ſurnamed Prath, and there ſettled his whole Army: The ſame day we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of our Ordnance in Carts made of purpoſe, and tooke the benefit of the Turkes Bridge, for the eaſier accommodating our ſelues, as you haue heard: yet was our King on foot, and had marched ſome few dayes before toward Leopolis, giuing vs dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions not to ſtirre, till the time appointed: For the Tartars were not yet appeaſed, but continued their accuſtomed manner of thefts and robberies, both in burning of Villages, and meeting with as naked men as themſelues; ſo that when we departed indeed, we went very ſtrong, ſending our Munition and Caria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, two dayes before we threw downe our Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; where-about, alſo there was ſome diſputing, whether we ſhould leuell them with the ground or no: for they ſeemed a good refuge, if occaſion ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to retire vnto.</p>
            <p>The 13. of October, the Turkes remoued againe a little beyond the Riuer of Prath, and encamped
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19303:18"/> themſelues three mile further. The ſame day our il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Prince continuing ſtill with the maine Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, aroſe at once, and marched to the further ſide of Iſter ouer the Turkes Bridge, by a Towne called Zaranie, in the Prouince of Checinen, and in the field that belonged to the Caſtle, where the Prince tooke vp his lodging, leauing the Lord <hi>Lermunth,</hi> and all the Germane Coherts to attend the Caria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Carts, and ſafe conduct the Artillery to the places appointed: For there were many ſtraglers of the Tartars, and Out-lopers of the Seruians and Walachians, that lay in waite for robberies, and ſpoiles, neither ſparing vs, nor the Turkes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, if they could ouer-maſter either, and ſo were no better then profeſſed Theeues: and therefore was this order taken in our marches, not to be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumuented, or made a ſpoile of in the breaking vp of a Campe.</p>
            <p>All the next day, being the 14. of October, we ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried at Zaranie, till the Cariages came together, which the day following, being the 15. we ſent very early to Camenicen, whether wee alſo approched with the maine Troopes by Sunne ſet. But the Coſſacks tooke another way, hauing many promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of gratification, both from the Turke and our ſelues, ſuch was their valour, deſeruing commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: ſuch were their enterpriſes compelling ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement. That night the Prince lodged in the Caſtle: and the next day the Commiſſioners returned with the Articles of agreement, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Honourable perſons preſented themſelues, who
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19303:18"/> were ſeuerally welcommed as Actors on the former ſtage of Warre, and turmoile, and louers of their Countrey, for whoſe ſakes, as you haue heard, they aduentured both eſtates and perſons, and were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to powre out their bloods, as they named it, for the croſſe of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>After the ſerious matters were debated, the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours diſmiſſed, and the affaires ſettled, they had ſome time to talk of other buſines, and amongſt the reſt of the Turkes diſpoſition, concerning whom one of the Basſhawes had diſcouered to the Polonians, while they were about their tractate of peace: how irkeſome and diſtaſting it was to the young Emperour, who many times in a franticke manner would excruciate and torment himſelfe with actions of diſtemperature, as throwing of his Turbane, beating his breaſt, and kicking his very Basſhawes, who durſt not reply, but were ſubiect to a very ſlauiſh proſtitution, and then would he fall to weeping, and wringing his hands to thinke vpon his inauſpitious actions, and vnfortunate attempts, remembring two eſpeciall times: one when with ſeauen thouſand of our Army, we ſet vpon 10000. Turkes, who made a braue ſalley on our Trenches, but were beaten backe with violence to their owne homes, at which he ſo ſtormed, that he called them Slaues, Vagabonds, and idle; as if they had played the Traytors of purpoſe to ecclipſe his glory, and obumbrate his renowne.</p>
            <p>Another: when the Coſſacks ſallyed vpon them, and ſlew ſo many of the Tartars, that they were
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19303:19"/> weary of killing, and ſo returned with a great prey and ſpoile into their owne quarters. But of all that fatall day, the 18. of September troubled and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented him, when he reſolued and ſet vp his reſt to ouer-runne vs at once, and came forward with ſuch impetuoſity, that we feared our ſelues, had not God fought for vs, and turned them backe with a great ſlaughter: yea, ſuch was our loſſe, and the doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of the victory, that all Europe rang with our ouerthrow: and in Hungary it was reported, how he was come as farre as Sendomiria and Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couia; but (God be thanked) it fell out otherwiſe, and as now the tale is told, a ſtrange accident affirgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them all, which we knew not then, nor doe we now preſume vpon, either as our deſeruing, or cauſe of preſeruation.</p>
            <p>The ſame day, an Earthquake chaunced in the Turkes Camp, in ſuch a fearefull and palpable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that the whole Army ranne out of their Tents, leauing the Emperour with ſome certaine Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berers and Ianizaries alone in his: who on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine demaunded; what was become of his Army? to whom it was anſwered, That part were gone vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Camiſado on the Polonians, and part were ranne out as amazed at the Earthquake. And part, now the curſe of <hi>Mahomet</hi> part them, ſaid he: What doe I here to be a ſcorne to you all, and a deriſion to poſterity? With that he ſnatched at a Semiter, and whether he meant to ſtrike at them, or diſpatch him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, they could not tell. But thus preuented, hee fell groueling on the ground, and vp againe with a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19303:19"/> diſtempred countenance, and wringing his hands: wherein his diſtemperature moued commiſeration, and they all ſtood amazed to ſee 14. yeares ſo appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſiue to diſtinguiſh betweene glory and ſhame: but were confounded altogether to heare him vtter theſe words, and vent out a paſſion in ſuch an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick manner.</p>
            <p>Oh God! that haſt giuen vs bread, and enlarged our Empire with the territories of Iewes, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and Kingdomes beſide? that haſt made the houſe of <hi>Othoman</hi> a ſcourge and terrour to all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and enlarged our renowne before any Prince vnder the Sunne: that haſt giuen vs a Prophet, and a Law, whereby our Alcharon is without oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: that haſt made our <hi>ſacra porta</hi> a wonder in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and aduanced our great Citty on a hill of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency, that the Nations may call <hi>Stanbole</hi> beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, and come from a farre to behold our <hi>Seralio.</hi> But what ſhall become of all this? Shall my youth, temerity, cowardize, or misfortune, adde a fatall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to this glory, or all my Aunceſtors victories wrapped vp in the Cipres cheſts of my deſtiny, and ominous proceedings? Shall all theſe Kingdoms re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume a new courage of reuolting, as if the Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane Empire were now at the higheſt, and my diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous childiſhneſſe the diſcouerer of the ſecret? Shall <hi>Othomans</hi> aſhes be metamorphozed into ſome horrid ſhape, to exprobrate my pufillanimity, and tell me to my face, I am more worthy of a rod then a Scepter? Shall <hi>Mahomet</hi> come from Paradiſe, and aſſure me, the gates ſhal be in the in the inſide againſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19303:20"/> me, for abuſing the truſt committed to me, and play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſuckling, when I was to fight his battailes in the field! Oh what an excruciation is this? Haue all my Prediceſſors done ſomething in the world as an addition of honour, and enlargement of their fame, ſaue onely my ſelfe, who am now ſo farre from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any thing worthy the leaſt report; that in ſteed of memorable actions and heroick attempts, I muſt returne with ſhame and diſcomfiture: nay, as they tell me, make a peace with a petty Prince and Prouince, when my Prediceſſours neuer pitched their Tents, nor aduanced the Standarts of our Creſſant: but had all the Princes of Europe with the wings of the winde, to flye in their faces, and yet to no purpoſe. And now, and now: am I borne to ſhame and confuſion? Oh God! Oh <hi>Mahomet,</hi> ſhall it be thus?</p>
            <p>To this, or the like purpoſe was that day ſpent by the young Prince, till at laſt, as you ſee the vpper ſtreames of a Riuer follow one another, miſchiefe att<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nded miſchiefe, and the cries of wounded men aſſured him, there was newes of another ſlaughter to torment him; then grew he ſo mad indeed, that no body durſt come in his ſight, had not the Muſty and ſome Doctors of the Law leuiated this phrenzie with honeſt diſcourſe; and from example, made a Cataplaſme as it were for his ſore: telling him the ſtory of <hi>Baiazet,</hi> whom <hi>Tamberlaine</hi> bound in chains, and of <hi>Soliman</hi> the magnificent, who after many glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious victories, ſaw the malice of a woman to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy his ſonne <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> and the reſt of his family:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19303:20"/> and of many others who had as great touches of grieuances as men were were ſubiect vnto, &amp; either beare them out brauely with the ſcorne of diſquiet, or recouered their renownes with a new induſtry, that was ſhrinking fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, by giuing way to feare or impatience: and therefore it is wiſedome and magnanimity to put in practiſe the beſt examples, and of all other things to yeeld to opportunity, as for the peace now to be conſidered on: There was no diſparagement to his Honour, and the greateſt Monarchs in the world haue yeelded to neceſſity in ſuch conſtraints. Againe, Fortune was not alwayes diſpoſed to be waaton, nor would at all times attend the chariot of Warre: therefore it was beſt yeelding a little to time, eſpecially now, when warlike Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons had learned this diſcipline, to encloſe an Army within Trenches, and Palliſadoes, that durſt not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the fury of a battail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, nor the violence of ſuch forces, as were ſure to make their way in the open fields. Beſides, experience had diſcouered this ſecret, that a well fortified Towne was now longer a win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and battering, then a whole Prouince in times paſt in ouer-running and conquering.</p>
            <p>In this manner, they pacified the young Prince, and prepared him againſt all manner of ominous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents: ſo that when the Treaty of Peace came in deed, the Commiſſioners proceeded, as you haue heard, and not onely e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fected that, which they went for: but returned with ſufficient reward, and equall acceptation, relating the matter as it chanced, and certifying our Prince with the whole diſcourſe,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19303:21"/> while he was reſident at Camenices.</p>
            <p>Thus far gentle Reader, hath one Letter brought me, and the buſineſſe, which being in a high Latine phraſe, and a Poliſh Character doth warrant, it came from ſome Gentleman of quality, or Souldier of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, or both in one man, who was ſure an actor in the ſame: and heerein I haue not failed in any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of matter, except in ſome circumſtance of time, or Ortography of proper names, miſtaking a Z for an L, or an s for an r, with ſuch like, &amp;c. which ſuch, as know the Countrey, may eaſely mend; and ſuch as know not, may yet vnderſtand the truth of the buſineſſe, without taking exceptions at the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of proper places, onely I muſt confeſſe I finde not the word <hi>Rex</hi> in all the Letter, but at the latter end: onely <hi>illuſriſsimus Princeps</hi> is often named, which whether it meane the Father or Sonne, I leaue it to him that can iudge by the coherence of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, and application of the diuiſions: what is done, is meerely for thy ſatisfaction; and what is to be done, will afford you the like pleaſure: For in both, you may ſee the mercy of a great God, and the vanity of a preſumptuous man: the one can pull downe the proud, and aduance the humble and weake: the other muſt confeſſe the changes of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, &amp; alteration of humane condition: or knock his knees together with feare and trembling, when with <hi>Belſhaſher</hi> he ſees the hand writing on the wall. Thus did the Aſſirian Monarch banquet in the bounds of the Sanctuary, and that in ſecurity, when yet the ſame night the Medes and Perſians beſieged
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19303:21"/> Babylon, and hee was betrayed into his Enemies hands with the loſſe of his life, and Kingdome. And thus did the great Turke threaten Poland, as hoping thereby to make a way into Europe, and the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne Seas, when yet within three moneths he was vtterly diſappointed, and compelled to entertaine a Peace, when in a youthfull iollity his heart ſcorned to entertaine any thing but reuenge or ambitious deſignes. Now the God of all bleſſings make vs thankfull for ſo great a mercy, that his benefits be not beſtowed in vaine, nor wee the ſonnes of men more ſtupid and ingratefull, then the bruit beaſts, that acknowledge his kindneſſe, and euerlaſting goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>I haue alſo (gentle Reader) another Letter for thee, which depends immediatly vpon the former, ſorting in euery thing to the truth: but that I finde a little diſcrepancy in the riſing of the Camp, which either may be miſtaken by the difference of <hi>ſtilo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo,</hi> and <hi>antiquo,</hi> or by the Kings going to Leopolis, before the maine Camps brake vp, and the Tartars were abſolutely appeaz'd, or drawne away by the Grand Signieur. I finde it tranſlated to my hand, and written from Leopolis to ſome man of Honour elſe where: but it hath neither date, nor ſuperſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: no, nor the Author hath ſubſcribed his name; at which I doe not wonder, becauſe it is but a Copy, nor would haue thee wonder: For it is a common thing in Letters of newes and occurrences, wherein all men would be glad to participate their ſecrets for the common good, but not publiſh the Authors for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19303:22"/> feare of priuate traducing: you ſhall haue it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as I finde it; and when you haue read it, then iudge whether it be worth the publiſhing or no. It thus begins.</p>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Copie of a Letter written from LEOPOLIS.</head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Gracious and Honourable Lord:</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THE fourth of October, wee departed from Lublinn, from whence I ſignified the preſent Occurrents, and hauing now expoſed our ſelues to a new iourney, we likewiſe a-new diſpoſed the order of our marches: For although the peace was concluded, yet the tydings of the Tartars and Valachians approches encreaſed, who being not withdrawne out of the field, would not withdraw themſelues from their beaſtly manner of ſpoiles, robberies, rapes, and cruelty: Wherefore to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent their reuenges, and ſecure our ſelues, the Troopes were thus marſhalled. Firſt, certaine Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets of Horſe-men, and Scowt-Maſters were ſent out; then the Vantguard with a Battalion on foot: then the Kings Maieſtie with his houſhold-ſeruants, and the Banner impreſſed the Armes royall; to wit, a white Eagle with a white croſſe diuided, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame <hi>tecum et pro te.</hi> This Enſigne conſiſting of fiue hundred, was gathered at the charges of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19303:22"/> Courtiers, and by them exquiſitely ſet out and ordered. After theſe, immediately followed the Kings Maieſtie, with a Troope of three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Dutch Horſe, being his Guard: then came ſuch Carriages as belonged to the King, and then ſuch as belonged to the Souldiers: And laſt of all followed the reare, which conſiſted moſt of Maſters of Pole. The ſixth day wee came to Zamoſchia, where there adhaered vnto vs about ſixe thouſand Dutch Horſe-men, whoſe Colonell was the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine of Marcinburg, and ſixe thouſand Foot vnder the conduct of Colonell <hi>Arnhem:</hi> ſo that thus ſtrengthened, we marched with greater ſafety, yet not altogether without perill, vntill wee came to Leopolis. For on the one ſide we ſaw the Country on fire, a moſt certaine Character of the Tartars im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, who burned all before them, and we had now attained vnto their aſhes: on the other ſide, wee might eaſely ſee many ſtragling Seruians, and Bulgarians, who as the Tartars delighted in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but vniuſtifiable Robberies, in which manner for all the Turkes proclamation they continued, till they were quite retired home.</p>
                     <p>The 8. of October, we lodged all night in a little Towne, which had been burnt by the Tartars cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Podlitez,</hi> and from thence determined the next day to go forward: but feare ceaſed vpon the Vaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, by reaſon the Scowts returned with newes, that our Wagons were ſurprized, and the noyſe went, they were ranſackt by the Tartars: but thankes be to God, it proued a falſe Alarum: onely ſome 4000.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19303:23"/> Tartars, and other of thoſe Nations appeared with a warlike countenance, and might haue been ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to take aduantage of our ſtraglers: but ſeeing vs ſo ſtrong, and ſo well ordered, they gaue vs leaue to goe forward, and we left them to their ſauage and vnnaturall immanity.</p>
                     <p>The day following, a Councell was called in a little Towne called Kimerton, and for as much as the maine body of the Tartars Army, was but three mile diſtant from vs, and that hauing done ſo well all this while, wee would be loath to make a ſhuffling end at the parting: we there encamped our ſelues, and aboad a whole day, and then taking the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring people into our cuſtody, we marched for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward toward Leopolis, and hauing the twelfth of October gayned the ſight of the City, euery man was cheared, and ſolemnly praiſed God for their former deliuerance. There came forth many of the Gentility to ſalute and receiue the King: and after them followed multitudes of people: an old cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to applaud the action of Conquerors, or wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſuch Princes, who elſe would be their owne caruers. It was verily woorth the ſeeing: For the King neuer rode with ſuch pompe and confluence into any City; and becauſe it was remarkable, and worthy of memory, I will hereafter compile it into a larger diſcourſe, and ſend it your Honour. In the meane time, to ſatisfie thoſe that deſire to know the preſent eſtate of our affaires, I will briefly make a ſummary collection, and intimate our deliuerances, as they chanced.</p>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:19303:23"/>
                     <p>Beyond all expectation a ſaluation is befalne vs: For wee are releaſed from the extreameſt perill whereinto wee were falne, not by our owne dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and power, but by the ſpeciall prouidence of God, who hath done great wonders for vs. Behold our matters were at the point of loſſe, our Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers being wearied and tyred with Turkiſh aſſaults: our powder and Munition failed our people, taſted of hunger and and wants. <hi>Kotkouite</hi> Palatine of the Wilde, and Generall of the Army died in the Campe: our Prince fell ſicke and ſadded our hearts, and many other inconueniences beſides the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of our men, threatned our ruine, and vtter ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion. But behold on a ſuddaine how comfort ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared: about the 2. of October a treaty of Peace was offered, and accepted by the Turke, for which purpoſe wee were contented to depute certaine Commiſſioners, who were accordingly entertained and admitted into the Turkes Campe, to wit the Caſtellan of <hi>Belſens,</hi> and the Palatine of <hi>Lublines,</hi> who went roundly to worke, but after the Turkiſh manner they ſtood vpon high tearmes of oſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vntill ſome, who ſtood in Tractalion with them, mittigated the heauy impoſed conditions, which continued vntill the 8. of October. In fine, the next day I know not by what ſpeciall working of God, the Turke caſting a ſide all the propounded Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and interiected cauils, accepted the <hi>Pacta an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiqua,</hi> which alſo was on both ſides confirmed and ratefied: Then were our Commiſſioners admitted to the Emperours preſence, and kindely receiued
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19303:24"/> and honoured with guiftes.</p>
                     <p>He alſo ſent vnto the Illuſtrious Prince <hi>Vladiſlaus,</hi> a liuing Elephant with many other thinges, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine regratulated him with Dogs, and certaine payres of hand Guns, made in the Low-Countries, and ſo the Peace was publiſhed, and the Articles brought to the King to <hi>Leopolis,</hi> the Campe remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning yet firme, and the Coſſackes continuing in their quarters.</p>
                     <p>At laſt the Turke retired his Army, and diuerted the Tartars, who all this while ſpoyled and burned the Countrey, hee alſo promiſed great guifts to the Coſſackes, which ſhould heereafter be ſent by Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, and whatſoeuer was equally demaunded, was on the Turkes part moſt Princely graunted; all which points conſidered, maketh this matter al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt incredible: For the like is not found in the Turkiſh Hiſtories, and in eſpeciall, that the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in perſon being in an expedition of ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, ſhould condiſcend to ſuch Articles of Peace, and be contented to returne home fruſtrated and diſappoined.</p>
                     <p>But theſe bee Gods ſecrets to preſerue vs, to the end that Chriſtendome ſhould not by our ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, bee further infeſted with Turkiſh Armies. For queſtionles if wee had fayled either in our Campe, or incounters, hee had paſſed without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trole, and the plaint Countrey would quickly haue beene ouer-runne by their multitudes, and outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Tartars who thought vpon nothing but ruine and deſtruction: what ſhould I inſiſt more vpon
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19303:24"/> this matter? great Peace hath imbraced vs, and comfort lighted vpon our heades vnlookt for: Our Campe ſhall be broken vp, and we dayly expect the Turkes Legate, for whom me Illuſtrious Prince <hi>Vla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſlaus</hi> tarries, we as ſuppoſe to conduct him to the King, who will abide 8. dayes at <hi>Leopolis</hi> to giue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for the diſcharge of the Souldiers, and ſetling of other matters behoofefull, partly for theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, partly for the good of Moldauia, and Podo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, with thoſe of Bogdonia, who are all included in the Articles.</p>
                     <p>After the diſpatch of theſe affaires, the King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to returne to Warſaw, as receiuing Letters out of Sweden, which are not altogether pleaſing vnto him: In the meane while the Gentlemen and Maſters are diſmiſſed, and many Souldiers, who are yet in the expedition haue order to returne, and a generall Commaundement is gone out to haue Prayers and Proceſſions in euery Church, yea I am ſure by to that time the newes came Cracow, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Citties, they will not ſpare for Bonfiers, and make a generall reioycing in euery place.</p>
                     <p>I know that theſe thinges will bee acceptable ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings to your Honour, the euent of other cauſes I will hereafter, ſignifie. Send the Conditions of the Peace, or if you will the Articles of agreement, and diligently write what elſe ſhall bee worth the relating, as I encounter with ſuch, as come out of the Campe: All I deſire now is, that this my dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence may bee commended, and dedicated vnto
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19303:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> your gracious fauour: I am promiſed a diſcourſe of the departure of the Tartars, and how they tooke their leaues of the <hi>Gran Seigneurs,</hi> when it comes it ſhall ſalute you with ſpeed, in the meane while Gracious Lord, if I reſt in your Fauour, I haue my deſire.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Datum Leopolis,</hi> 
                           <date>14. October, <hi>Stilo nouo.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>CONDITIONS OF Peace, betwixt the Emperour of the Turkes, and his Majeſty of Poland, <hi>Sul. Dato</hi> 9.th of October, 1621. <hi>Stilo Nouo.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. INprimis, <hi>Staniſlaw Saliſhowskis Secretarius Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius,</hi> ſhall <hi>ex nunc</hi> goe with the Turkiſh Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour vnto <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> there to attend the comming of a great Ambaſſador, which the Kings Majeſty ſhall ſend, and the ſaid Ambaſſador ſhall alwayes remaine at the <hi>Sacra Porta,</hi> like the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors of other Chriſtian Potentates: and in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect a principall Chawſe ſhall preſently be diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to goe with our Commiſſioners vnto his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, and a great Turkiſh Ambaſſador follow, to the end that <hi>Pacta antiqua abvtra<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> parte,</hi> which are all recorded, may bee ſworne vnto, confirmed, and ratefied.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To the end that the Coſſacks may not hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth damnifie the Turkiſh Empire: both ſides bind
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19303:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> themſelues to preuent the ſame: and ſo oft as the Turkiſh Emperour in this reſpect ſhall haue cauſe to require the adminiſtration of Iuſtice, the Kings Maieſty ſhall bee obliged to performe the ſame. In which reſpect the Tartars likewiſe ſhall abſtaine from all manner of hoſtile inuaſions againſt the Kingdome, as in more eſpeciall the Turkiſh Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour hath vndertaken to hinder their paſſage at <hi>Och<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kora,</hi> and if beyond expectation either part ſhall be damnified, by the other reſtitution ſhall be made, and the Tartars puniſhed: but in the Vaſt and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuided Wilderneſſe, vntill their equall diuiſion and limitation follow, it ſhall be free for the Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars and Coſſackes to Hunt wilde Beaſts, and it ſhall no whit impeach the <hi>Pacta Conuent:</hi> although in this reſpect they may happen to fall together by the eares, and ſeeke their reuenges.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When the <hi>Tartar Chrim</hi> ſhall goe vpon any expedition to ſerue the Turkiſh Emperour, he ſhall not touch or damnifie his Maieſties Lands, and to the end that in this caſe either may know his bounds there ſhall bee Commiſſioners <hi>ex vtra<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> parte</hi> ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and by them certaine limits appointed, as alſo Ouerſeers for the blacke Sea, and thoſe rouers.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Reſpublicae Pol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a,</hi> yeeldeth and accordeth henceforth to pay vnto the Tartar the accuſtomed Tribute which hee ſhall demaund by his Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, and in this reſpect the Hoſpodar of Walachia, ſhall alwayes be an vnderſtanding peaceable man, and a Chriſtian, and ſhall helpe to keepe the Tartars in Office, &amp; gouernment, that they attempt nothing
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19303:26"/> 
                  <hi>Contra pacta,</hi> or if they doe to receiue puniſhment, according to the nature of the offence and tryall: And if his Maieſty ſhall haue ſuch occaſion, then ſhall the Tartars aſſiſt him againſt his enemies: In a word, they ſhalbe obliged to ſerue the Kingdome.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is granted, that <hi>Chochim</hi> ſhall be deliuered vnto the Hoſpodar of Walachia, with all the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purtenances formerly belonging to that Fort.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Vnto all thoſe which are the Turkes enemies, ſhall the King and Kingdome of Poland, be likewiſe Enemies, and a friend vnto all his Friends: and in the ſame manner ſhall the Turkiſh Emperour be obliged to the Crowne of Poland.</p>
               <p n="7">7. All theſe Conditions were ſworne by the ſaid Commiſſioners, and they were written in Poliſh, Turkiſh, and Latine, and the following great Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors in like manner <hi>facta renouatione</hi> on both partes ſhall confirme the ſame, and continue the maintaining of the ancient <hi>Pacta</hi> by their Oathes: They were alſo vnder written by the Viceer of the Army of Turkes, the Mufty, and a Doctor of Law: but on our ſide, by <hi>Staniſlane Zorarmiski, Caſtellan</hi> of <hi>Belſen,</hi> and <hi>Iames</hi> of <hi>Sobniski</hi> the Palatine, Sonne of <hi>Lubelski,</hi> in the name of the Kings Maieſty, and of the Generall <hi>Staniſlane Lubomirski,</hi> Captaine of <hi>Zando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir:</hi> with the other Commiſſioners deputed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Thus (gentle Reader) thou haſt likewiſe the laſt Letter with the conditions of peace, as they were then ratified by the Turks, and King of Poles Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners: there were alſo read in publique the old
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19303:26"/> contracts, containing the limitation of their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and the mentioning their friends and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates, with all tributary Prouinces, and many other things impertinent at theſe times: all which I haue omitted to trouble you withall, reſoluing only to ſatisfie you with a plaine truth of the end of the Warre, and to tell you a wonder in the making the truce: the vſe is meerely to ſet out the glory of God, who can turne the frame of heauen about, and bring that to paſſe with eaſineſſe, which the wiſedome of man thinketh impoſſible, and the pollicy of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes determineth to contriue another way: and to diſcredite the oſtentation of Princes, who out of their owne preſumption can boaſt of great matters: but when the cauſe comes to bee decided in the Court of Heauen, they are laughed to ſcorne, and a contrary ſentence condemneth them, as delinquents to the Maieſtie of God, and offenders againſt their owne ſoules and conſciences.</p>
               <p>Since this, I haue alſo receiued other Letters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Marchants from Conſtantinople, dated the 10. of December, which make mention of the Grand Signieurs being at Andrinopolis, but is not yet come to the great Citie: onely the Haga of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizaries, and certaine Officers of the Seralio are ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued to prepare the Pallace, and clenſe the Towne, that both Court and Citie may be fit for his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment. And amongſt the reſt, there is one thing moſt remarkable, that his Vnkle <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> when he was depoſed, did Propheſie of this peace: and in a manner foretolde, that the <hi>Ottaman</hi> Empire was at
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19303:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> the higheſt, and ſhould no further enlarge the ſunne, but rather decline, and ſee their renowne ſhadowed with malignity of time: But becauſe his Spirit was not anſwerable to his greatnes, the Ianizaries neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected him: nor his wiſdome for lacke of publicke conuerſation, as being alwayes kept Priſoner, ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory to the gouernment, hee was the ſooner put downe, and ſo as yet he remaines vnſtrangled, and peraduenture vnreſpected.</p>
               <p>There now remaines no more, but for the Poles to fortefie their confines, &amp; ſtand vpon their Guard for all this Contract of amity, and treatice of purification, conſidering the fry of Nations, that lye Eaſtward from them, who either are enemies to Chriſtian Religion as Idolaters, and Mahumetans: or indeed of no Religion, as running the violent race of Sauagenes and beaſtiallity, all which good care and vigilancy will preuent, conſidering as I haue often ſaid, they are naked men, haue no Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and are to ſeeke when they come to Trenches and Fortifications: Yet for all this good ſucceſſe: and proſperous euent of the Warre? I would nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue them too preſumptuous, or elated, as though their owne Arme of fleſh had done it: nor tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rous or exanimated though they heare of the Turkes preparation againſt them. For it is not the ſound of 2. or 300000. of men can conquer Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and Kingdomes, but the extraordinary valour of well diſciplined Souldiers, nor are they likewiſe to boaſt with the <hi>Syreans</hi> that they can licke vp the duſt of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and transferre the Diadems of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19303:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> at their pleaſure, but to know there is a God of Battailes, that made <hi>Gideons</hi> 300. ouerrunne the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianites,</hi> and will doe wonders for his Church in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of the watchings of the Dragon: yea I make no doubt but that the ſame God, which hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered Chriſtendome from the Turkes excurſions as you haue heard, will alſo deliuer the Proteſtant Princes from the Popes Curſes, and Antichriſtian threatnings, as you ſhall ſhortly ſee, And ſo I end with the Poet:
<q>
                     <l>O melibace Deus nobis haec otia faecit,</l>
                     <l>Nam<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> erit ille mihi ſemper Deus, illius vram</l>
                     <l>Saepe tener noſtris ad ouilibus imbuet agnus.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
